<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answere to a letter cum priuilegio.</title>
            <author>Saint German, Christopher, 1460?-1540.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1535</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21558.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100189</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836039</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836039</idno>
            <idno type="VID">282</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11297)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 282)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 21:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answere to a letter cum priuilegio.</title>
                  <author>Saint German, Christopher, 1460?-1540.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[128] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Tho. Godfray,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1535?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Christopher Saint German.</note>
                  <note>Regarding royal supremacy and various points of religion.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and address from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H.</note>
                  <note>With a final contents leaf.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 659 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:282:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:282:1"/>
            <p>¶An an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to a letter. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Cum priuilegio.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:282:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:282:2"/>
            <head>¶Here begynneth the anſwer.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Haue receyued youre letter wherby I perceiue that ſyth your returnyng i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to your contrey: <hi>Ye</hi> haue herde that there is yet he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in London moche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munycati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; great dyuerſytie of opynions vpon ſuche articles as were ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye were here. And ye haue alſo written to me at a good le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth all the articles that be noyſed ther in your countrey to go yet abrode here in the cytie. And thervpon ye deſyre me to write vnto you my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyt / what I thynke is to be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thoſe articles: &amp; ſurely that is a right great requeſt for me to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhe. For though I entende to ſpeke the truthe therin / &amp; do ſo in dede: yet paraduenture ſome men wyll be offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with it / &amp; nat take it playnly after my meanyng: but neuertheles / truſtyng that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt parte of the people be nowe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe dayes enclyned to take all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges
<pb facs="tcp:282:3"/>
to the beſt. I wyll nat for the opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyon of a fewe / fully deny your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt theri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but ſhall ſhewe you with good wyll my conceyt to all your articles / for I truſt charitie hath moued you to that deſyre. And I wyll nat recyte here your artycles perticulerly togither / but wyll an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere to them after the ſame order as they ſtande in your letter. And ſo / euery man that ſhall happen to rede this anſwere ſhall knowe the order of the articles i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your letter.</p>
            <p>And fyrſt ye ſaye / that many in your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey reporte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhuld be a ſayeng here about London / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kyng hath many newe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites gyuen hym / by that he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognyſed to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupreme hed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erth vnder god of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / &amp; ye deſyre me to ſhewe you my conceyt what I thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke therin / &amp; I wyll fyrſt with good will ſay ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what to it to ſatiſfye your deſyre.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:282:3"/>
            <head>¶ Whether the kynge by that he is recognyſed to be ſupreme heed vnder god vpon erth of the church of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / haue therby any new power giuen hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer his ſubiectes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had nat before. The firſt cha.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He kyng / by that he is recognyſed by the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liamente to be the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme heed vnder god vpon erth / of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Englande / hath as I take it no newe power gyuen hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge but that lyke as before that reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gniſyon made / he had all ſuch po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer his ſubiectes ſpirytuall and temporall / as to a kyng belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth by the lawe of god: ſo after the ſeyde recogniſyon / he had the ſame power without alteration / &amp; none other but that. And therfore he maye nat as I ſuppoſe by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:4"/>
of that recogniſyon / take vpon hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any auctority that our lorde gaue only to his apoſtels or diſcyples / i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpirytuall miniſtratyon to the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. And though he may nat / yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> recogniſyon was nat to al inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes voyde / for by reaſon therof the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer of the kyng is more euyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly knowen than it was before that re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cogniſyon made: for before that re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cogniſyon / the clergye had gretly defaced the power of kingꝭ in this realme. And for a more playne declaration of this mater / it is to be conſydered / that there are ſome thynges that are called mere ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall / and that be ſo in dede. And ther be ſome that haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led mere ſpirituall / whiche neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe perteygne to the power of kynges and princes. The thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges mere ſpirituall be theſe: The conſecration of the ſacrament of
<pb facs="tcp:282:4"/>
the auter / the makynge of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucyons / the gyuyng of orders / &amp; the miniſtratyon that ſaynt Paul ſpeke of. ad Corin. iiii. Whan he ſayd of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf &amp; of other Apoſtels &amp; diſcyples of Chriſt thus / Let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man eſteme vs as miniſters of Chriſt / &amp; as diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſatours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteryes of god / wherby he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode princypally the miniſtratyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacramentes. And ſuche mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration the kynge may nat take vpon him / ne he intendeth it nat. I knowe well that a kynge maye be a preſt: yea / &amp; a byſſhop alſo / &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might he lawfully miniſter al ſuch ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges if he lyſt: but I wolde nat thynke that it were an increſynge of his honour to do ſo: for the honoure of a kynge ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth ſpecyally i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doyng iuſtyce vnto his people / as it appereth. Pſ. xcviii. where it is ſayd: The honour of a
<pb facs="tcp:282:5"/>
kyng loueth iuſtyce. And one poi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of, iuſtyce is / to ſe the miniſters vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do their duty. And therfore if byſſhoppes were neglygente in doynge their miniſtration to the people / the kyng might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de them to do it: &amp; that were more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to him than do it hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe. And though as it appeareth, ii. Par. xix. Kyng Ioſaphat ordeyned iugꝭ in all the cyties of Iuda: and that in Ieruſalem he ordeyned Leuytes &amp; preſtes / &amp; princes of famelyes that they ſhuld iuge the iugement and cauſe of our lorde. &amp;c. Yet it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth nat that he made them preſtes no more than he made Amaryas a preeſt: for thoughe he appoynted Amaryas to be cheife preeſt / yet it appereth that he was a preſt before And alſo though kyng Dauid ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poynted the preſtes and leuytes to their offyces / as appereth .i. Par.
<pb facs="tcp:282:5"/>
xxiii. &amp; xxiiii. Yet it appereth nat that he made any of them preeſtes. Alſo trouth it is / that euery kyng is bounden to miniſter iuſtyce vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his people / accordyng to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of his realme. And may ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to that intent be called a mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter: but yet that miniſtration is all in a nother maner / than is the miniſtration of the ſucceſſours of the apoſtels: for the miniſtration of a kynge / is the miniſtration of power / iuſtyce &amp; ſouerayntie: and to it ar neceſſary great poſſeſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / honour and ryches / to maynteyne his eſtate. And the miniſtratyon of the other ſtandeth in ſpirytuall ſeruyce to the people / in mekenes / ghoſtly counſell / preachynge and teachynge in all charyte: in ſomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che that none ſhulde be mery in god / but they ſhulde be mery with him: none ſhulde be in heuyneſſe / 
<pb facs="tcp:282:6"/>
but they ſhulde ſorowe with him: and to theſe miniſters is neceſſary ſuffyſaunce without abundaunce: and honeſt pouerty is nat directly agaynſt that miniſtration: &amp; they ought alway to haue a contynuall deſyre that the people ſhulde lyue in ſuch brotherly loue &amp; quyetnes that there ſhulde nede no miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of iuſtice by the high powers to be vſed amongeſt them. And if any ſuche happened to come / they ſhuld feare gretly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to come through ſome defaute in them. And ſurely wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any gret variaunce &amp; trouble ryſe among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people / it is nat vnlyke but that ſome parte of the occaſyon therof roſe fyrſte through the defautes &amp; neglygence of ſome of the clergye. Than ſyth it is right highly expe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the miniſtration of a price to haue habunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of poſſeſſyons
<pb facs="tcp:282:6"/>
as is ſayde before / howe maye he take any other miniſtration vpon him that agreeth nat with that ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bundance. I knowe no man that wyll perſwade the kynge to take thoſe powers vpon him: but I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue writen to you my conceyte / that in caſe that anye man wolde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him to it hereafter / that ye ſhall knowe before howe as me ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth his perſwacyon ought to be alowed. The other that haue ben called in tyme paſte thynges mere ſpirytuall / &amp; be nat ſo in dede / be very many wherof I ſhall recyte parte: but to recyte all / it wolde be very tedyouſe both to you &amp; to me: but if ye / &amp; other that be lerned in the kynges lawes wolde dilygent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly enquere for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ye ſhulde fynde many mo than I wyl reherce here</p>
            <p>Fyrſt it hathe ben taken in tyme paſt as a thynge mere ſpirytuall / 
<pb facs="tcp:282:7"/>
that the byſſhop of Rome oughte as the vycare generall of Chriſte / to gyue all ſpirytuall promocyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and benefyces through criſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dom. Alſo that he &amp; other byſſhops vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him / ought euen by the law of god to viſyte all preeſtes / curates and houſes of relygyon throughe cryſtendome. Alſo that no prince / might taſke his clergy for any cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe without lycence fro Rome: that the deuiſyon &amp; diſtinctyon of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe fro paryſſhe / is a thynge ſo mere ſpirytuall / that no man may do it but the clergy. That ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuary in churcheyardes / is lykewyſe ſo ſpirytuall / that the clergye muſte nedely order it: and that therfore they be all accurſed that watche a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny man in the churchyarde. That no byſſhop ought to be made with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out the popes bulles: and that he ought to haue Annates for them.
<pb facs="tcp:282:7"/>
That the clergye oughte to haue correction as of thynges mere ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall / of auoutrye / fornicacyon / ſymonye &amp; vſury: and to ordre ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trymony / tythes / oblacions / and periury in ſome caſe. &amp; of dyuerſe other thinges wherof it is no dout but they haue holden plee in tyme paſt / rather by a cuſtone &amp; by a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feraunce of princes / than for that they be mere ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all / or that they had auctorite ſo to do by any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medyate power of the law of god. They haue claymed alſo as thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gꝭ mere ſpirytuall / the prouynge of teſtamentes / makyng of letters of adminiſtrations / ſequeſtrations / pluralytes / vnyons / &amp; diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons / &amp; dyuers other / whiche be nothyng mere ſpirytuall at all.</p>
            <p>And ſuch powers kinges &amp; prices might take into their handes lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully if they wolde / without offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge
<pb facs="tcp:282:8"/>
the lawe of god. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe I ſpeke not this / to the intent that ye ſhulde take my meanynge to be / that I wolde haue it ſo done in dede: but that I wolde haue it knowen vnder what maner they haue their power in ſuch thynges to the intent they myghte the more mekely / &amp; the more charytably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe theyr power herafter amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the people / than they haue done in tyme paſſe. And it is no doute but that many of the clergy haue ſet ſo gret diligence to maynteyne their power &amp; iuryſdiction in ſuch mixt thynges / that they haue the leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garded the miniſtration in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge &amp; techynge / &amp; in the thingꝭ before reherſed that be mere ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all in dede. And that were moch more ꝓfytable to the people to be mayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyned / &amp; contynually put in execu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon than the other be.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:282:8"/>
            <head>¶ Of dyuerſe thinges concerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the power of the byſſhop of Rome and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtatutes made in the .xxv. yere &amp; xxvi. yere of kynge Henry the eyght / which treate of the ſayd power. The .ii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>FYrſt ſuche power as the apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtels and diſciples hadde of Chriſt / they vſed / &amp; might laufully vſe in the begynni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the churche vnyuerſally i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all places wher they came / &amp; none had any more power in one place than in another.</p>
            <p>Alſo after the paſſyon of Chriſt the ſucceſſours of the apoſtles and dyſcyples were appoynted to vſe their power within a certayn cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuite / but that appoynteme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was onely by the power &amp; law of man / &amp; nat by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mediat power of god.</p>
            <p>Alſo at the counſell of Nycene / Rome was nat taken for the heed
<pb facs="tcp:282:9"/>
of the churche: ne the byſſhoppes there had nat than any other aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytie / but as euery other byſſhop had. And that appereth thus: The byſſhop of Alexandre is there in the ſeyde counſell of Nycene fyrſt ſpoken of before the byſſhoppe of Rome: &amp; if the byſſhop of Rome had ben there heed of the churche / it ſhulde nat haue ben ſo. And the byſſhop of Alexandre was by the ſeyd counſell appoynted for his dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ocyſe to Egypte or Lybia / &amp; Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tapolim. And the biſſhop of Rome was appoynted to that he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to haue before: &amp; it was farther decreed / that at Antyoche and other prouynces the honoure ſhulde be kepte to euery churche.</p>
            <p>Alſo after the ſeyde counſell of Nycene / there was gret varya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwyxte dyuerſe byſſhops / who ſhuld be the hygheſt byſſhop. and
<pb facs="tcp:282:9"/>
the byſſhop of Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme toke him ſelf for higheſt / and called him ſelfe prince of byſſhops And after as Platyne / De vitis ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pontificu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / writeth it was ordeyned in the tyme of Focas the emperour / that Rome where Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyface the third was than biſſhop ſhulde be the heed of all churches / whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it folowed that the ſeyd Bonyface ſhulde be taken as heed of all byſſhops and preſtes. And greate varyaunce was after who ſhulde be next ſeate to Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / &amp; who the thyrde / the fourthe / &amp; the fyfth / wherof is mencion made Diſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> xxii. cap. Sacro ſcta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; cap. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinopolitane / &amp; ca. Renouan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: by al which lawes it appereth euydently that there was none of the ſeyde byſſhops that pretended to be the heed of the vnyuerſall churche of Chriſt / that is to ſaye / 
<pb facs="tcp:282:10"/>
of the whole congregation of all chriſten people: but only to be hed of all other byſſhops &amp; preſtes: for if any wolde haue pretended to ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ben heed ouer al chriſten people he ſhulde haue pretended to haue ben heed ouer the ſeyde emperour Focas / &amp; ouer all other kynges &amp; princes alſo: and it is nat to thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke that the ſeyde Focas wolde haue aſſented therto. And neuertheleſſe by occaſion therof / many of the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſours of the ſeyd bonyface / haue taken vpon them to be the hed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole vnyuerſall churche of Chriſt wherby they haue pretended to be heed ouer emperours &amp; kynges: &amp; that emperours &amp; ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges oughte to be obedient vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; with helpe of biſſhops in cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys &amp; realmes and of other that haue ben highly auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced in the clergy / &amp; that more fauoured y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſſhops of Rome tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:10"/>
their owne naturall princes / they haue put emperours &amp; kyngꝭ that wolde any thinge reſyſt that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence many tymes in gret dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger &amp; ſomtyme vtterly diſtroyed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And yet the very truth was / that they had no power gyuen theym but onely that they ſhulde be the heed ouer other byſſhops whiche they had as Platyn ſayth &amp; ought therby to haue onely at metynges and congregations ſome preemy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of place and power of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng / if they lyſt before any there byſſhops: &amp; yet neuertheleſſe they made emperours &amp; kynges &amp; their people beleue that they had ſuche power / and brought theym in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe alſo / that they were bounden to gyue credence to the clergye in all ſpirytuall maters / and that to doute at the popes power was he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy: &amp; ſo through puſyllanimitie
<pb facs="tcp:282:11"/>
and wylful ignoraunce of princes and their people / and throughe a confederacy of Byſſhoppes / they were therin right gretly deceyued but whan the parliament in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid xxvi. yere &amp;c. recognyſed the kyng to be the ſupreme heed in erth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der god of the churche of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de they vnderſtode by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terme: chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / the hole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation of all the people within this realme / aſwell of the clergy as of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lay people: &amp; that the kynge is the heed of them all / as he is in dede: for it had ben a recogniſyon of ſmall effecte / to haue recognyſed hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hed of the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye only / that was before heed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his ſubiectes ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all &amp; tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. And ſo by that recogniſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the kynge hath none other auctoritye ouer his ſubiectꝭ but as he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: ſo that he maye nat vſe any power mere ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all / that our lorde
<pb facs="tcp:282:11"/>
gaue onely to his apoſtels &amp; diſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: as to conſecrate or make ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolucions / ne any other lyke / as is ſayde before. And if percaſe the parlyamente &amp; conuocacyon alſo had expreſſely graunted to the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with the ſeyd name of the ſupreme heed: ſuch ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al auctorityes / it is no dout / but that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graunt had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> voyde: for they haue no auctorite to chaunge the lawe of god. And if this be trewe / it wyll be very harde to tell what auctorite or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is taken by the ſeyde recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon fro the byſſhop of Rome that he had before the ſeyd recogniſion made: for the extorte powers that he toke vpon him by occaſyon of that name in this realmeꝭ were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken fro him before by the ſtatutes made in the ſeſſone holden in the ſeyd .xxv. yere. &amp;c. But that name of heed of all byſſhops remayneth
<pb facs="tcp:282:12"/>
yet vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nat taken away bi any ſtatute / &amp; that maye appere in this maner. The ſeid ſtatute of .xxvi. is only that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng ſhall be ſupreme hed vnder god vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erth / of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / wherby is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ought to haue ſuche po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this realme ouer his ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al &amp; temporal / as to a kyng belongeth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of god / as is ſayd before: &amp; with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may well ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / that one may be hed biſſhop &amp; miniſter in thynges mere ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all ouer the ſame people: but than ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myt that he be ſo / yet what power he ought to haue therbi ouer other biſſhops is to be ſene / and to gyue other occaſyon to treate more tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly of that mater. I ſhall ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſhewe my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceite theri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And that is / that it ſhulde ſeme that he ſhulde thereby haue this preemy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence / to haue the hygheſt ſeate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
<pb facs="tcp:282:12"/>
all other byſſhoppes. And if he wolde preache / that he ought to haue the place before all other / as is ſayd before / &amp; theſe preemynen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; other lyke remayneth yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / if he cam into this realme for ought that the ꝑliament hath don: &amp; if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll ſay that he ought therby to haue &amp; vſe alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of a biſſhop in mere ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all thingꝭ as in gyuyng ordres / makynge of preſtꝭ / makyng of excoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / &amp; ſuch other in all places wher he ſhuld come / aſwell w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out his owne dyocyſe as within: to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be anſwered / that if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall counſell whereby Rome was made hed of al other churches / had ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the biſſhop of rome ſhuld haue had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of a biſſhop vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſally in all other byſſhops dio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyſes through criſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> than the ſeyd general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel wold haue
<pb facs="tcp:282:13"/>
expreſſed openly that power / and wold alſo haue reuoked the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell on Nycene / which appoynted the biſſhop of Rome to his diociſe and that in all other prouynces / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honoure ſhulde be kepte to euery church. But foraſmuch as the ſeid generall counſell dyd nat ſo / it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that it inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded that the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell of Nycene ſhulde ſtande in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte: &amp; that the byſſhop of Rome ſhuld ſtyll kepe him to his diociſe as he dyd before / hauynge only by that name ſuch preemynence at the generall metynge of byſſhops / as before appereth in whoſe diocyſe ſoeuer they mette: neuer the leſſe I wyll nothynge ſpeke determy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natly in this mater: but remytte it to them that haue auctoritye. And than if it be thought by the kynge and his parlyament that no hurte can come hereafter to the comen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>welth
<pb facs="tcp:282:13"/>
/ though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſſhop of Rome be ſuffred to kepe ſtyll his name of the heed byſſhop of cryſtendome / bycauſe the kynge natwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge that name maye enioye the name of ſupreme heed vnder god vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erth of the church of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: they may ſuffre it contynue: but if they ſe lykelyhodꝭ / that if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name be ſuffred to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynewe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> than by colour of that name / he wyll pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende hereafter to haue power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue kynges &amp; princes / as his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours haue done in time paſt: than maye the parlyamente repell that name as to this realme for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: &amp; it wyll be a very good dede to do it for the mayntenance of the whole comen welthe. But as yet it is nat auoyded / bycauſe bothe names may ſtande togyther to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueral intentes as before appereth. How may any man than reſyſt the
<pb facs="tcp:282:14"/>
ſeyd ſtatutes but he reſyſt god: or how may any man ſay that if he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to the ſtatute / that he ſhulde fal therby fro the vnyte of chriſtes church / ſyth the vnyte therof ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth nat in that poynte / whether Rome be heed churche of all other churches or nat: But tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay in this mater / that the parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment dyd nat wel to recognyſe the kynge to be ſupreme heed in erthe vnder god of the churche of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande: where ſaynt Paule ſayth ad Ephe. v. Man is the hed of the woman / as Chriſt of the church: &amp; alſo he ſayth ad Coloſ. i. He is the heed of the body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche: that is to ſay Chriſt. and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſaid i. Corin. xi. The heed of Chriſt is god: &amp; ſo ſay they / the parlyament ſhulde haue holden lyke ordre / as ſ. Paul dyd &amp; haue recognyſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kyng was ſupreme heed vpon
<pb facs="tcp:282:14"/>
erth vnder Chriſte / to whom god was heed / &amp; that the parlyamente erred in that they kept nat y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordre that. ſ. Paule. did. And truly this is a daungerouſe ſayeng: for if the ꝑlyament erred therin / than were no man bounden to obey the ꝑlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in that behalfe: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑliament may nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge do againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of god: neuertheleſſe it is apparant that the ꝑlem<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t dyd well &amp; varyed no thinge fro ſ. Paule: for it ſayth that the kyng is the ſupreme heed vpon erth vnder god / and that is true that he is vnder god. And yet in that it ſaythe / that the kynge is ſupreme heedde vnder god / is nat Chriſt excluded: for god is Chriſt and Chriſt is god / and the whole Trinitie is in Chriſte: And ſo he that is vnder god / is vnder chriſt ſo Chriſte is God / and ſo God and Chriſt is all one.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:15"/>But if the ꝑliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t had recogniſed the kyng to be ſupreme heed vpon erthe vnder god / of the churchc of Englande / but nat vnder Chriſte than had they erred in dede / &amp; no man had ben bounden to haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the kyng vnder that maner as ſupreme heed. &amp;c. But here it is nothing ſo. And I dare wel affer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that it was neuer the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / to make any diſtynctyon or dyuerſytie betwyxt god &amp; chriſt ne to exclude Chriſte fro the heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp of the church: &amp; if the ꝑliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t had ſayde expreſſely that the kyng was ſupreme heed. &amp;c. vnder god and Chriſt / than noman wold ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue taken any exception to it. And ſtatute is nowe of the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte: and ſyth it is now a lawe of the realme / it muſt be iudged ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the groundes and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of the lawe of the realme / and
<pb facs="tcp:282:15"/>
vndoutedly they wyll iuge the ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tute to be of ſuch effecte as I haue ſayde before: &amp; that that was the very meanyng of the makers ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of / for the wordes therof proue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycyently that it was ſo: &amp; though they do ſo / yet is that iugement no thynge agaynſt ſaynte Paule: for with that it ſtandeth verye well / that Chriſt is the heed of the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che / &amp; that god is alſo the heed of Chriſt / as ſaynte Paule ſayth.</p>
            <p>¶ Alſo whan Rome was made heed of all other churches / as Pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyne ſayth it was: yet it is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne what princes were warned to be at that counſell / &amp; what nat. And if any Prince or Countrey were nat warned to be there / than that cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell bounde nat that pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / and no man can iuge for certayne that the kynge of this realme that tyme beynge had ſuche warnynge
<pb facs="tcp:282:16"/>
for it was in the tyme whan there were many kynges in this realme and whiche of them were warned and whiche nat / no man can tell. And if this realme were nat boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de by the ſeyde generall counſell to accepte Rhome as hedde of all churches bycauſe it had no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge: but hath by cuſtome aſſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to it / than is that cuſtome the thynge that ſhuld bynde this real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to it / and nat the generall coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell / and than it is no doute if the parlyamente ſee a hurte folowe to the comen welthe / by that cuſtome but that they maye: yea / and are bounde of iuſtyce to redreſſe it.</p>
            <p>Alſo / though it were admytted that this realme hadde warnynge and were therefore bounde by the ſeyd generall cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell as other real<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes were: yet for as moche as a
<pb facs="tcp:282:16"/>
generall councell ſhulde be holden at certayne tymes appoynted by the lawe to redreſſe wronges done to the people. And it is well kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen throughe chriſtendome: that popes in tyme paſte haue delayed ſuche generall counſeyls / further than the lawe wold this many ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Therfore if the wronges done by popes / ſhulde nat be reformed before a generall counſell / the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple mighte be longe greued / and haue no helpe of longe tyme: and there is no reaſon why they ſhuld ſuſteyne wronge any one daye ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyally by him that dyffereth the meanes whereby they might haue remedye. And therefore the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament hath good auctoritye to remoue ſuch wronges i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: and ſo haue all other Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes that be in lyke maner greued as this realme was.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:17"/>¶ Alſo though it were nat the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente of the ſayde Phocas to take any power fro princes / but onely to make Rome the hedde of other churches: yet neuertheleſſe the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes haue by occaſyon therof taken great power fro princes / as whan they pretended to gyue all ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all promocyons thorowe all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome / and to do dyuers other thynges vnder the pretence that they were thynges mere ſpirituall as in the fyrſt chapiter of this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere appereth: And whan they pretended to make perſonall cyta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions to whom they wolde &amp; cauſe them vpon payne of curſynge / to appere at Rome aſwell byſſhops as other / that all appelles ſhulde be made to Rome / fro all byſſhops of cryſtendome / &amp; that all biſſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes ſhulde be ſworne to them: And that they myghte prohybyt what
<pb facs="tcp:282:17"/>
bokes: &amp; preachers they wolde by their owne auctorite. And certayn it is that they optayned all theſe powers more thorough the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of princes / rather than by the lawe of god.</p>
            <p>Alſo many of the ſayd pretences made by the byſſhops of Rome / &amp; dyuers other nat here remembred were dyrectly agaynſt the power of other byſſhops / that they had re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued of the immedyate gyfte of god. And byſſhops coulde nat ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ben compelled to haue ſuffred ſuche vyolence if they wolde haue reſyſted it: And therfore great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faute &amp; offence of conſcyence was in them / that they wolde wylfully ſuffre ſuche wronges nat onely to their owne hurte: but alſo in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to a whole confoundynge of al truth / and of al good comen welth in many countreys.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:18"/>¶ Alſo / for as moche as the byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome / natwithſtandyng the ſeyde ſtatutes. And alſo nat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandynge any other ſtatute made in this preſent parlyamente ſhall haue as moche auctoritye in this realme as his predeceſſours had at the ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell of Nycene: no man may ſay that they that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thoſe ſtatutes declyne fro the vnytye of Chriſtes churche or fro the goſpel: but he ſey alſo that the ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell of Nycene dyd ſo like wyſe: and that no man wyll ſaye as I ſuppoſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Of prayenge to ſayntes and worſhyppynge of them. The thirde cha.</head>
            <p>THis is a good prayer: lord I beſech the in the honour of our bleſſed lady &amp; of all the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:282:18"/>
&amp; vertues that thou gaueſt vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to her: for the which gracyous gif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes I &amp; al other ar ſpecially bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to honour &amp; loue both the and her / that thou to thy honoure &amp; to hers graunt me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I aſke if thou know it expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for me &amp; if nat thy wyll by done &amp; nat myne: And I ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe verily y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they that made the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tani entended none other wyſe but that all the prayers that be made therin to our lady &amp; to other ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhuld be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as prayers vnto our lorde: that he for al the graces that he gaue to them: gyue vs his grace &amp; help vs in all our neceſſyti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es: But no man ought to aſke any peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our lady as thought ſhe of her ſelf hath power to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it &amp; there be many alſo that wil ſay fer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther that oure ladye of her owne power dyd neuer yet any myracle but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lorde only of his power
<pb facs="tcp:282:19"/>
to ſhew that he had accepted &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued her vertue / wherby other might be encouraged to labour to haue lyke vertues as ſhe had: dyd it. And they ſay alſo that we may nat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt oure ſoules holly to her ne praye her to putte awaye oure ſynnes: for none maye put awaye ſynne but only god. And further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more I can right well agree / that ſayntes of them ſelfe / ne by their owne power can nat here our com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>playntes / ne knowe the honoure that we do to them: but ſyth they be alwaye in the ſyght &amp; fruicyon of the Godheed / I ſuppoſe that they by the power of god / ſe them and knowe them / as in moſte cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt glaſſe. And that for this cauſe the deuocyon that the people haue to ſayntes / if it be well ordred / ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth to the honour of god: for that ſuche deuocyon ryſeth to them for
<pb facs="tcp:282:19"/>
the graces &amp; vertues that our lord of his mere goodneſſe gaue to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here in this worlde: &amp; therfore it is very lyke that the ſayntes knowe that deuocyon ſo done to theym to his honoure. Alſo it is written .i. Corin. xiii. Charitas nunquam excidit. Charyte neuer falleth: that is to ſaye / ſuche charytie as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath in this worlde at his deth ſhall nat decaye: but ſhalbe moche more in heuen than it was here: &amp; thervpon it ſemeth to folowe / that ſyth they here i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this world of their charyte had compaſſyon of all the people: but more ſpecyally of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhewed them their greifes / &amp; prayed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their comforte / that they do lykewyſe nowe: for els it ſhuld ſeme that their charyte were nat ſo great nowe as it was than: for no man can haue compaſſyon of any perſone in eſpecyall / but he
<pb facs="tcp:282:20"/>
knowe the thynge that greueth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and wherfore he doth ſpecially co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne / wherefore as it ſemeth / it muſt nedes folow / that the ſaintes in heuen / through the goodneſſe &amp; power of god / here &amp; knowe ſuche complayntes as be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made to them: for els their charytie in partyculer neceſſyties of men ſhulde nat be ſo greate as it was whan they were here / and that ſhulde be agaynſte the wordes of ſaynte Paule / befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re reherſed. And than whether ſayntes in heuen therevpon praye for vs or nat: Verely I thynke there is no vocall prayer in heuen for if ſayntes by a vocall prayer ſhulde ſhew all our ꝑtyculer peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; compleyntes to our lorde / &amp; praye him to helpe vs with kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges and beſechi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges / as is vſed here in erth / whan we wolde haue oure peticyons graunted in thys worlde
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:20"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:21"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:21"/>
/ ſo that it be onely for god and to his honoure / and that god for that loue ſo ordered to his loue / wyll ſomtyme here our complayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes: yet it is no doute but that that complaynynge to ſayntes is the moche lower degree of prayoure than a prayoure and a complaynt made to oure lorde for hym ſelfe: that is to ſaye that he for his owne goodnes and for the paſſyon and dethe that he ſuffered for vs and for all mankynde / wyll here oure petycyons: and whye the people ſhulde be ſo delygently called on to vſe the lower degree of prayer that is to ſaye to praye to Sayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / and that the excellencye and worthyneſſe of the hygher prayer that is to ſay to god for him ſelf is ſo ſeldome declared vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as it hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in tyme paſt: Me thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth it is moch to be merueyled
<pb facs="tcp:282:22"/>
Neuertheleſſe I can well agree / that the fyrſt complaynynge / that is to ſay to ſayntes / is right good: for our lorde wylbe honoured and loued in dyuers maners / ſomtyme for himſelfe / ſomtyme for his ſain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes: &amp; alſo he wyll ſomtyme ſhewe to the worlde / that he wolde his ſayntes ſhulde be honoured for the graces that he frely gaue to them in this worlde: to gyue other cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to endeuoure them ſelues to haue lyke vertues: but he wyl nat that the thanke be holly ſtollen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him and gyuen to them: ne yet the ſayntes wolde in no wyſe haue it ſo: and therfore it wylbe very dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gerouſe to ſuffre the people to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke their complaintes to ſayntes or to ſay their deuocyons before yma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges after their owne deuocion and affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / for vndoutedly many of them but they be ofte admonyſhed
<pb facs="tcp:282:22"/>
howe to ordre theymſelfe therein / wyll honour the ymage. And alſo pray to the ſayntes with a ful truſt that they ſhall optayne of them all that they do aſke / and that ſhulde be to the derogation of the honour that ought only to be gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to god as is ſayde before. And than to your other queſtion / whether it be lawfull to honoure ſayntes / or to ſaye anye prayers to oure lorde to their honour. It is as me ſemeth / but a lytle queſtyon / for ſythe it is lawfull to worſhip a mortall man for the auctoritie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oure lorde hath ſet him in here in this worlde: or for that he is our fader or mother / or for the vertue that oure lorde of his goodnes hath giuen hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this mortall lyfe / whiche neuertheleſſe he maye lyghtly loſe: moche more it is lawfull to honoure them that be in heuen / for the vertue that our
<pb facs="tcp:282:23"/>
lorde of his free gyfte / gaue vnto them here in erth / whiche they be ſure they ſhall neuer loſe. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe / me thynketh there may be put ſome dyuerſytie betwixt ſuche ſaintes as be canonyſed by ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re / and the olde auncyent ſayntes that haue alway be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taken for holy by a ful comen &amp; vnyuerſall aſſent of all the people throughe an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde inſtyncte and ſpeciall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of the holy ghoſt in the hertꝭ of the people / &amp; bytwixte ſuche as haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of late tyme canonyſed for ſayntꝭ at Rome for mony: &amp; by the ſpeciall labour &amp; callynge on of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that hath ben of the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of lyuyng as they were. As of byſſhops for byſſhops / preſtes for preſtes / relygyouſe for relygyouſe and ſuch other. For it is very lyke that manye haue laboured for the canonyſatyon of ſuche ſayntes as
<pb facs="tcp:282:23"/>
haue ben of the ſame degre of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge as they be: more of a pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate loue to theym ſelfe / and for a commendatyon of that waye of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge that they be of / than for the pure loue of god / or for encreaſe of vertue amonge the people. And nowe wyll I therfore ſhortly as I can more playnlye ſhewe my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte / what ſayntes a man maye vndoutedly beleue to be in heuen. And fyrſt he maye beleue all them to be in heuen / that be wytneſſed by ſcrypture to be holye and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: As it is of oure Lady: ſaynte Iohan Baptyſt: the .xii. apoſtles ſaynte Paule / ſaynte Stephan / &amp; of the thefe / to whom oure lorde hangynge on the croſſe ſayde:</p>
            <p>This daye thou ſhalte be with me in Paradyce / and dyuers other who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Scrypture wytneſſeth to be bleſſed / and alſo of them that be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membred
<pb facs="tcp:282:24"/>
for holy. Eccleſi. xliiii. And ad Hebre. xi. he may alſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke them aſſuredly as bleſſed / that haue ben accepted as holye &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of longe tyme by the whole aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent of the vniuerſall chriſten peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple throughe wytneſſe of the holy ghoſt gyuen them in their hertes that they be holy and bleſſed / as it is of the auncyent martyrs that in the begynnynge of the church / ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fered deth for the fayth of Chriſt &amp; of other holye men &amp; women / that haue ben accepted for holy by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men aſſent of all the people of cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome: for the goodnes of our lorde is ſuch that he wyl nat ſuffre his vniuerſall people where they intende wel renne holly into an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynion that is vntrue / &amp; ther fore I ſuppoſe verily that the deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the people was ſuffycient cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſacion to many of them that be
<pb facs="tcp:282:24"/>
in ſcrypture before any Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was made of ſcrypture. And lykewyſe I ſuppoſe that the greateſt ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gthe &amp; auctorite of the newe teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment roſe in the begynnyng of the churche by a full belefe / that dayly roſe in the hertes of all the cryſten people to that that was preched bi the apoſtles / &amp; written by the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gelyſtes in the ſeid teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before any Canon was made of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But of ſayntes that haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> canonyſed at Rome for money / for affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or for any ſuche other worldly conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. Whoſe vertue and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles: if they were byſſhoppes or preſtes were ſpecyally extolled &amp; ſet forth by biſſhops &amp; preſtes: and if they were of any relygyon / their vertues &amp; myracles haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely extolled by them of the ſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lygyon: ſo that tas it ſemeth a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocyon hath ben brought to them
<pb facs="tcp:282:25"/>
in to the hertes of many perſones rather by mannes polycye than by inward inſtyncte of the holi ghoſt: of ſuche ſayntes it is more dowte whether they be holy or nat. And therefore to complayne to them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermynge them precyſely to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and bleſſed / hauyng none other proufe that they be ſo. but the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may lyghtly erre / ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth nat ſo ſure to complayne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to as to the other. Howbeit I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende nat by this ſayenge to affer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me precyſely / that they ſo canony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by wytneſſe of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be nat holy. But I wold auoyde the preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that in ſuche caſe take vpon them to iudge them for holy that only belongeth to god to iuge vpon. And I ſomwhat doute the more at ſuch newe canonyſacyons bycauſe the famouſe clerke Iohan Gerſon in a treatiſe that he calleth
<pb facs="tcp:282:25"/>
the declaratyon of the defautes of men of the churche / auertyſeth the generall counſeyle / to conſyder if it were well done to canonyſe</p>
            <p>Charles duke of Brytaygne / nat withſtandynge the great multy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſayntes that were canony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before. And vpon the eyghte treatyſe of Magnificat. he vnder this ſygne. &amp;. ſayth / that there is a legend / which ſayth / that a deed dogge was worſhipped in Vie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na for a ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / wherfore it ſemeth right expedyent that all the people / but moſt i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſpecyall the clergy &amp; relygi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſe pray deuoutly to o<hi rend="sup">r</hi> lorde that the rulers may through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpecyall gyft of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt now in this da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gerous time / know whoſe canony<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in his ſight / &amp; who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe nat / &amp; than by a comen aſſent to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferme them / that they ſhall after dilygent prayer thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke to be holy in
<pb facs="tcp:282:26"/>
ſuch maner that they ſhalbe taken here after by all the people as holy and bleſſed to the honoure of god and encreaſe of vertue / through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good example &amp; bleſſed lyfe that they ſhall here &amp; rede of the ſeyde gloriouſe ſayntes / and nat to be bounde to beleue that any other is holy &amp; bleſſed / but they ſo aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſed / as is afore ſayd. And nowe wyll I ſomwhat ſpeke of abuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the maſſe / for that foloweth next after the ordre of your letter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶Whether there be any opinyon amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there be ſome abuſyons concernynge the maſſe. The fourth Chapiter.</head>
            <p>WHere ye haue written to me / that there is a ſayeng in your countrey / that many here aboute the Cytie ſhulde fynde defaute a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:26"/>
dyuers abuſyons that they preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to be in dyuers ceremonyes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge the maſſe. I aſſerteyne you it is euen ſo as they ſaye / that there be many of that opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / they ſticke fully to the effecte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe that is the gloriouſe ſacrament: But at dyuers thynges which as they ſaye / be abuſed in that behalfe they fynde right gret defaute. and they ſaye further alſo / that if any man fynde defaute at ſuch abuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that dyuers of the clergye wyll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non do that in them is / to cauſe it to be noyſed amonge the people / that he erreth in the ſacramente. &amp; they ſaye alſo that many ley peple haue ſuche a ꝑnytie &amp; redyneſſe to gyue credence to ſuch reportes / be they true or falſe / that a man ſhall be anon halfe condempned or that the mater be any thynge knowen as it is: and ſurely I thynke it is
<pb facs="tcp:282:27"/>
true as they ſay / that there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great dyſorders &amp; abuſyons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernynge the maſſe: How be it / I wyl nat at this tyme treate ꝑtycu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for dyuers cauſes: but ſhall beſeche our lorde to put it in to the mynde of all chriſten pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces to loke dilygently vpon them and other lyke / &amp; ſe them reformed: for it is nat in the power of any other to do it / &amp; therfore if they ley nat to their handes / it is to feare that lytell good wyll be done in ſuche maters: but that the olde way and the olde abuſyons wyll contynew as they haue done in tyme paſte / which vndoubtedly ſhulde be to the hygh diſpleaſure of god / hurte of the comen welth / and right great danger to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules of many ꝑſons.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>¶Of pardons and abſolutions. The .v. chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:27"/>THe power of grauntynge of pardons and makynge of abſolucyons hathe ben ſo farre abuſed in tyme paſt diuers wayes that it hath nat ben onely executed againſt the intent of the grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tour that is to ſay of our maiſter chriſt but alſo ſo great couetyſe hath ben ſhewed therby / that gret grudges and murmures haue ryſen by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſyon on therof in many countreys and that nat without great cauſe. And one cauſe hathe ben this:</p>
            <p>Though our maiſter Chriſt ſayd to Peter in the name of all the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. Mat. xvi. What ſoeuer thou loſeſt vpon erth ſhalbe loſed in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: by which wordꝭ al the apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtels &amp; their ſucceſſour had aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite to make abſolucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / a pena et culpa / that is to ſay / for the ſynne &amp; fro the payne dew for the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne: yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſucceſſours of Pe. haue only taken
<pb facs="tcp:282:28"/>
vpon them to execute that power by waye of grauntyng of ꝑdons / as though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted onely to Peter &amp; his ſucceſſors And for a further profe that all the appoſtles had one lyke power in makynge of abſoluſyons by theſe wordes: Quodcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſolueris. &amp;c. it is ſayd in the popes owne lawe Diſtincꝭ. xxi. cap. nono. Thus: The power of byndynge &amp; loſing Peter fyrſt toke &amp; the other appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtels in lyke feloſhip with hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / toke lyke honour &amp; power. And .xxiiii. q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. loquitur. It is ſayd that the other Appoſtles were as Peter was / endewed in one lyke felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip both of honoure and power. And ſyth the power of all the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles by wytneſſe of the lawe / that is called the popes owne law is lyke: why ſhuld than they that pretende to be the ſucceſſours of
<pb facs="tcp:282:28"/>
Peter / vſurpe that power only to them ſelues: And yet that vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion appereth the more plainly by cauſe that in the .xviii. chapiter of Mat. our lorde ſayd to his diſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples generally y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame wordes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reherſed / that is to ſaye: what ſoeuer ye loſe vpon erth ſhalbe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in heuen: &amp; it muſt of neceſſyte be taken / that by that worde diſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples / he ment either his apoſtels which be ofte called in the goſpell diſcyples: or els that he ment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the .lxxii. diſcyples: or els that he ment them both. And if he ment therby the .xii. apoſtles only / than euery one of them had yet by thoſe wordes as hygh power as any of the other had. And if he ment ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by the .lxxii. diſcyples &amp; the .xii. Appoſtels alſo: than hathe euery preeſt to this day power to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te pardon / bycauſe he is the ſucceſſor
<pb facs="tcp:282:29"/>
of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .lxxii. diſcyples / &amp; if they haue ſo a I thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke verily it is no doute but they haue: it is greatly to be merueled / why they or biſſhops ei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther wold renounce &amp; forſake that power y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was ſo playnly gyuen to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Chriſt. Howbeit ſome men wene that it was done to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they by that occaſyon &amp; other lyke might make one byſſhop ſo hygh i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auctorite aboue all other biſſhops and preſtꝭ / that he ſhuld be able to matche with ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges &amp; princes: &amp; if byſſhops &amp; preſtꝭ haue that power than maye kynges &amp; princes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to exerciſe that power for the renounſynge of their prede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſoures in that behalfe byndeth them nat. And neuertheleſſe vpon that renounſynge / hathe folowed this inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenyence / that none coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de haue ſuche pardon or abſolucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but fro Rome / and that nat frely / 
<pb facs="tcp:282:29"/>
but for greate ſommes of money / excepte only that to pleaſe Cardy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles / Archebyſſhoppes and byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes. It was agreed that Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynalles and Archebyſſhoppes / ſhulde haue power to graunt an hundreth dayes of pardone: and byſſhoppes .xl. dayes: but as for preſtes which were and be conuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaunt dayly amonge the people in euery paryſſhe / and that mighte haue done moſt good therwith to the peple: as I ſhall ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what touch afterward was no prouyſyon: for all the ſtudy &amp; dilygence was to ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alte buſſhops. and here it is to be noted howe great diſſymulatyon and pride was in this conueyance aſwell in the ſucceſſours of Peter as of the other Appoſtles in thoſe dayes: For if that power had ben onely graunted to Peter and his ſucceſſours / than might nat he nor
<pb facs="tcp:282:30"/>
his ſucceſſours haue grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted his power / nor no parte therof to any other: for it can nat be proued nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther by the letter of the texte / ne yet / that it ſhulde be the intente of Chriſt / that he wolde that Peter ſhulde make ſuche deputyes. And he made nat only Cardinals / arch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byſſhops &amp; byſſhops his deputies to graunte ſuche pardon as he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted them / as is aforeſayde: but he graunted alſo many tymes ſuche deputacyon condycyonally to all preſtes ſeculer &amp; reguler / as though they ſhulde haue their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer onely fro him: &amp; therefore he graunted his pardons many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes vnder this maner / that who ſoeuer wolde gyue ſuche a ſomme of money to the reperation of S. Peters church at Rome / or to ſom other intent expreſſed in the bulles that they ſhuld amonge other thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:282:30"/>
haue auctorite to take an able ghoſtly father / ſeculer or reguler / that ſhulde haue power to aſſoyle them fro all theire offences / &amp; alſo fro the payne dewe for it / excepte that comenly in ſuch pardons ſom thynge was alway reſerued to Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me / as for a remembrance that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhulde nat forget the way thyther. And howe coulde the pope grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te power to ſuche confeſſour to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoyle anye man fro payne / if the confeſſoures had nat had that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer before of god. And if euery preeſt haue ſuche power of god / as I thynke verily he hath as well as any byſſhop: than it ſemeth that it were good that they ſhuld be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to vſe that power heraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by way of abſolucyon frely / to the eaſe &amp; conforte of the people / &amp; they nat to be dryuen to go to any byſſhop for it. And if that power
<pb facs="tcp:282:31"/>
were ſo ordred / than all the good dedes that any man ſhulde do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuche abſolucyons by waye of penaunce or other wyſe / ſhulde be auaylable to hym to encreaſe his ioye in heuen / and nat only for put<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng away of paine for their ſinne paſſed, And as it ſemeth it is very conuenyent that ther ſhuld be ſuch an abſolucyon a pena et culpa in chriſtes church: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of chriſt is called the lawe of grace &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And the olde lawe was called the lawe of iuſtyce: and alwaye in the olde lawe / by a full &amp; parfyte contricyon equiualent to the actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſynne: the ſine / &amp; alſo the payne for the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne was put away / excepte onely the origynall ſynne / &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhuld ſeme that the new law ſhuld be more fauourable tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that was / and that is as I ſuppoſe by ſuche abſolucyons / wherby all the
<pb facs="tcp:282:31"/>
good dedes that the penytent ſhal do after the abſolucyon ſhalbe tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned holly to his rewarde in heuen as is afore ſayde. And further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more if it were admytted that the ſucceſſours of Peter ſhulde haue only the power to graunt pardon yet neuertheleſſe it appereth euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme paſt rizt gretly abuſed their power therin: for the wordꝭ that gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> power in that behalf / be the wordꝭ before reherſed: Whatſoeuer thou loſeſt vpon erth ſhalbe loſed in heuen: by which wordes it appereth that the meani<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of our lorde was / that Peter ſhuld haue non auctoritie to loſe any man by that graunte: but ſuch as were bounden to ſom thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before ſuche loſynge. As if a man had offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / &amp; wer by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that offence bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den to a certayne paine for it / that tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pet<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; his ſucceſſors
<pb facs="tcp:282:32"/>
ſhulde haue power to releaſe it. And that if he releaſed that payne in erth / that god wold releaſe it in heuen. And I can right well agre that he had that power &amp; dyuers other alſo as I haue ſayde before But how farre his ſucceſſours ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue abuſed that power: it maye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere thus: They haue graunted their pardons nat onely for relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge of payne for ſuche ſynnes as were done afore the tyme of the graunt. But they haue graunted alſo / that all they that wolde giue ſuche a ſomme of money / ſhulde haue power to chuſe them an able ghoſtly father / that ſhulde aſſoyle them as well of the offences done after the pardon graunted as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and alſo of the payne for the ſame. And ſomtyme ſuch perdons haue ben graunted for drinkynge of ſuche a cuppe or ſuche a bolle
<pb facs="tcp:282:32"/>
or for offrynge to ſuche an ymage / or for ſome other lyke ſmall conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations / &amp; what abuſyons theſe haue ben / &amp; howe dyrectly againſt the intent of the graunte it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant. And it is appera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo that if the ſucceſſours of Peter ſhulde onely haue power to graunt ſuche pardon / &amp; that onely for offences done before the graunte / that than that graunte ſhulde delyuer but fewe from payne for their ſynnes: in compariſon of the multytude of chriſten people: for euery penytent maye nat incontynent after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance go to Rome fro ſo farre countreys &amp; aſke pardon there for their offences paſſed. And therfore it ſemeth that our lorde whiche is all goodneſſe / wolde nat make a grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ſhuld ſerue to ſo lytel a purpoſe as that ſhulde do / but that it ſhulde ſtreche more at large a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge
<pb facs="tcp:282:33"/>
the people / wherfore as I ſuppoſe the ſeyd grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhal ſtretch aſwell to the ſucceſſours of all the apoſtles &amp; diſcyples: that is to ſay aſwell to all byſſhops &amp; preſtes as to the byſſhops of Rome / &amp; that ye ſhall nat take my wordes in this behalf / as thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges clerely vnware<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any auctorite or example of the goſpell. I ſhall ſhewe you a playne example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as it ſhuld ſeme by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward wordes of the goſpell ſhuld ſtretch only to the apoſtles &amp; their ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours. &amp; that yet all preſtes haue auctorite therby. And that is vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the inſtitucion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aulter: for it appereth. Mat. xxvi. that o<hi rend="sup">r</hi> lorde made his mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his .xii. diſcyples / wherby as it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth / is to be vnderſtand only his xii. apoſtles. For <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. it is ſayd ex<g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſate downe to ſupꝑ w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his .xii. apoſtles / wherat he inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:282:33"/>
the gloriouſe ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / &amp; ſayde to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Take ye this &amp; ete it / this is my body that is gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for you / ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ye this in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of me / &amp; if by theſe wordes: make ye this in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of me: none ſhuld ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue power to conſecrate but only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtels &amp; their ſucceſſors / which moſt ꝓperly be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be biſſhopꝭ than ſhuld al inferyor preſtes whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che be comenly taken to be ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors to the .lxxii. diſcyples haue no power to conſecrate. &amp; yet the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men experyence ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate. And they do wel therin / for they be preſtes aſwel as the apoſtels were. &amp; ſo it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to be taken / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent of o<hi rend="sup">r</hi> mai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter chriſt was y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all preſtes ſhulde do it. &amp; why tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal it nat be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be his entente y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde / that what ſoeuer any preeſt loſed vpon erth / ſhuld be loſed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſwel as
<pb facs="tcp:282:34"/>
any biſſhop: rather than that they ſhuld conſecrate: for theſe wordes ſeme as wel to be ſpoken to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyples as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles / as apꝑith Mat. xvi. before reherſed. And if any man wyll pretende that there be other auctorities for grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyng of pardons than theſe that I haue before reherſed / or that wyl prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that byſſhops onely haue that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer &amp; noon but they / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may aſwell graunt ꝑdon before the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to put awaye the payne for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſine that ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted after the grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſwell as before: It wyl be well done that his reaſons be herd in the ꝑlyament. And if his reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the prouf thervpon ſeme ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyent / than to folowe it: And if nat I thynke verily that the ꝑlyament is bounde in conſcye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de all preeſtes to erecute that power frely fro henſeforth to the eaſe and
<pb facs="tcp:282:34"/>
conforte of all the people without takynge any thynge for it: and I dare ſay further in this mater that ſuche preachers as haue in tyme paſt inſtructed the people / that the byſſhop of Rome ſhulde haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to graunt ſuch perdons by the vertue of the ſuperhabundance of the meryttes of Chriſtes paſſyon / and of the meryttes of martyrs &amp; ſayntes in heuen / wherefore they deſerued rewardes aboue theire offences / haue nat inſtructed the people truly therin: for there is nat a ſaynte in heuen / but that he hath through the mercye of oure lorde / more rewarde in heuen / than euer he deſerued of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe: &amp; if percaſe any ſuch ſuperhabundance of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytes of Sayntes remayned / yet the byſſhops of Rome had neuer power to diſtribute thoſe merytes by waye of pardon to none other:
<pb facs="tcp:282:35"/>
For our lorde neuer gaue ſuch po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer vnto them / ne yet to diſtrybu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te by waye of pardons the mery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of his paſſyon.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Of reſtitucyon. The .vi. cha.</head>
            <p>WHere ye write vnto me / that there is a ſayeng in your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey / that there ſhulde be ſom here about the cytie / that ſhulde doute whether reſtitucyon be neceſſarye to ſaluatyon: wherefore ye deſyre me to write to you ſomwhat of my mynde concernynge reſtitucyon. I thinke verily that as a man is prohybyte that he ſhall do no theft wherin is conteyned that he ſhall nat take his neyghbours goodes wrongfully / that by the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement he is prohybyte to retaygne theym wrongfully / and
<pb facs="tcp:282:35"/>
that if he haue ſuffycient to reſtore and knoweth alſo to whom reſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucyon ſhulde be made / that he is bounden vpon payne of brekynge of the ſayde commaundement / to make reſtitucyon. And further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more omyttynge the diffynycyons of doctours vpon reſtitucyons / that is to ſay: to whom / by whom what tyme / and vnder what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner reſtitucyons ſhuld be made v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the lawes Cyuyll and Canon whereof many doctoures haue in tyme paſt treated at great length. I wyll ſomwhat ſpeke of reſtytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons vpon caſes concernynge the lawes of the realme / to gyue ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytuall men and other that be nat lerned in the lawes of the realme / courage to haue more knowlege of them hereafter / than they haue hadde in tyme paſte: for in many caſes it canne natte be knowen
<pb facs="tcp:282:36"/>
without them: where reſtitucyon ought to be made and where nat.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt if a man haue iſſue / two ſonnes one before eſpouſels / and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother after and dyeſeaſed of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des in fee: &amp; after his deth his ſonne borne before eſpouſellꝭ / entreth as heyre / &amp; taketh the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytes / he is bounden in this caſe to make reſtitucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his yonger bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of the lande &amp; alſo of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytes. For the yonger brother after the lawes of the realme is heyre. But if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elder brother in that caſe dyeſeaſed / &amp; his heyre entre: that heyre is nat bounde to make anye reſtitucyon. For by the olde grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of the law / the yonger brother in that caſe by his laches / for that he wolde nat entre in his brothers lyfe / hath loſte his lande for euer. But that is to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / wher the brethren beſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes to one woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:36"/>
And alſo wher the lande is fee ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple / &amp; in both the ſeyde caſes the elder brother after the lawe canon is heyre / and ſhall enheryte.</p>
            <p>If a man haue landes in fee ſymple by diſcent fro his father / &amp; dye without yſſue of his bodye / &amp; haue no heyre on the parte of his father / wherfore the nexte heyre of the parte of his mother pretendi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to be his nexte heyre / entreth &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the profites / that heyre is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den to make reſtitucyon to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde of whom the lande is holden: for the lorde oughte to haue it by the lawe as his eſchete. But if a man purchaſe landes in fee / &amp; dye with out heyre of his body / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for lack of heyres of the parte of his father the heyres of the parte of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / ſhall haue the lande and nat the lorde by eſchete.</p>
            <p>If a man haue landes in fee by
<pb facs="tcp:282:37"/>
dyſcent tro his mother / and he ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth a feoffament therof. &amp;c. And feoffe maketh a leaſe for terme of lyfe to a ſtranger y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remaindre i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fee to him agayne and to his hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. And after he dyeth withoute heyre of his body / in this caſe the heyres of the parte of hys father ſhall haue the lande. And if the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayndre in that caſe were that it ſhuld go to him and to his heyres of the parte of his mother / yet the remayndre ſhuld go to his heyres of the parte of his father: for thoſe wordes of the parte of his mother be voyde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe / as they ſhulde be if a man wold infeoffe another to haue to him and to his heyres of the parte of his mother: for the heyres of the parte of his father natwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding thoſe wordes ſhal haue the lande / and therefore in both the ſeyde caſes: if the heyres
<pb facs="tcp:282:37"/>
of the ꝑte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother entre i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / they be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reſtore it to the heyres of the ꝑte of the father.</p>
            <p>If a man that hath landes in fee by dyſcent fro his mother / dyeſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed / &amp; the landꝭ diſcende to his ſon &amp; heyre: and that ſon &amp; heyre dyeth without heyre of his body in this caſe / the heyres of the parte of his graundmother ſhall haue the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de</p>
            <p>And if either y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heyres of the part of the father or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heyres of the ꝑte of his mother entre / they be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make reſtitucyon to the heyres of the parte of his graundmother.</p>
            <p>A man hath two ſonnes by ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wyfes / the one ſon purchaſeth landes to him &amp; to his heyres / and dieth without heyre of his body: if his brother in this caſe entre as heyre / he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to reſtore it to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or her y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is heyre to his brother on his fathers ſyde: for the grounde
<pb facs="tcp:282:38"/>
of the lawe is / that one of the halfe blode ſhall neuer be heyre to him that he is but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> half blode vnto.</p>
            <p>Alſo if a man holde .ii. houſes of two ſeuerall lordes by heryote cuſtome / wher the cuſtome is that no heryote ſhall be payed but of quycke catell: &amp; he hath no quycke catell but one horſe &amp; dyeth / one of the lordes ſeaſeth the horſe. &amp; after the other Lorde fyndeth the ſame horſe / &amp; ſeaſeth him as his heryote in this caſe he his bound to reſtore the horſe to the lorde that fyrſt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him: for by that fyrſt ſeaſynge he hath by the lawe of the realme right to the horſe / &amp; the other hath loſt his herriot for that tyme. And the ſame lawe is / if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> holde .ii. acres of lande of .ii. ſeuerall lordꝭ by knyghtes ſeruyce / &amp; by owelty of feffeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; dyeth / his heyre with in age in this caſe that lorde that
<pb facs="tcp:282:38"/>
fyrſt ſeaſeth the body hath rizt to it</p>
            <p>If a man holde an acre of la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by knyghtes ſeruyce by prioritye / &amp; an other acre of lande of another man by knyghtes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce by poſteryoritye &amp; dyeth ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed his heyre beynge within age / and the lorde of whom the lande is holden by poſteryoritye / ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid infaunte as his warde. In this caſe he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to reſtore it to the lorde by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritye: for by the lawe the ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the body belongeth to him / excepte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame aunceſtre holde any la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of the kyng by knyghtes ſeruyces: for if he dyd the kynge ſhall haue the prefermente of the body by his prerogatyue whether the lande were holden of hym by prioritye or poſteryorite: in cheyfe or as an eſchete.</p>
            <p>If there be two ioynt tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes
<pb facs="tcp:282:39"/>
of a wode / &amp; the one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelleth al the wode / &amp; taketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> money to his owne vſe: in this caſe he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reſtore the half of that money to the other ioynttenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: for though the law gyue no remedy to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ioynttenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for it: yet it ware<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth nat him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath the money / that he maye with conſcyence retayne it.</p>
            <p>If one ioynttenaunt take all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greſſe and frutes to his owne vſe / where els they ſhuld haue ben loſt for laches of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other: there he is nat bounde to reſtore any parte: but if his felowe wolde haue taken his parte / &amp; the other wold nat ſuffre hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / than he is bounde to reſtore hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ꝑte. And ſo it is / if one ioynte tenaunt or tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in comon / ſowe the one half of the errable grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; leueth the other halfe for his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe / &amp; whan the corne is ripe / his felowe taketh halfe of the corne / pretendynge that the halfe is his
<pb facs="tcp:282:39"/>
through all. In this caſe he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to reſtore the whole to him that ſewe the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue goodꝭ ꝑſonall and alſo reall / as a leaſe for terme of yeres: a wardſhip or ſuch other and after ſhe taketh a huſbande / &amp; he dyeth after whoſe deth his exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutours taketh al the ſayd chatels / aſwell reall as parſonall / in this caſe the executoures be bounde to reſtore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyfe of the chatels reall: but nat of the chatels perſonall / nor no parte of them / her neceſſary werynge apparell onely excepted.</p>
            <p>A man hath a maner / whereto comen is appe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daunt. And alſo an aduouſon / and he of his mere mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon maketh a feoffame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd maner / &amp; putteth nat i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe wordꝭ cum ꝑrine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciis. &amp;c. the feoffe occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pieth the comen. And alſo wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the aduouſon falleth void he preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth
<pb facs="tcp:282:40"/>
to the aduouſon: in this caſe he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to reſtore the feoffer for the aduouſon. But the comen he may lawfully occupye ſtyll. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If the ſonne be attaynted of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonye in the lyfe of the father / and after hath the kynges chartoure of pardon. &amp;c. and than his father dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth / ſeaſed of lande in fee ſymple and the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſo attaynted / entreth as heyre: In this caſe he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to reſtore the lande to the lorde of whome the lande is holden: For though he haue his chartoure of pardon / yet his blode is ſo corrput by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> attayndour / that he may nat be heyre to anye man: And if the landes be entayled / he is bounde to let the kynge haue them during his owne lyfe. And than after his deth / the heyres of his bodye ſhall haue the landes accordynge to the fyrſt gyfte. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:40"/>If an infant make a couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to gyue one for his meate &amp; drinke for ſuche a certayne tyme / a horſe / and whan he hath ben with him ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordynge / he gyueth him the horſe And alſo he ſelleth him another horſe for a certayn ſome of money i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this caſe he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reſtore the laſt horſe to the infant agayne / but nat the horſe that he had for hys meate and drinke. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>An infant of the age of .xx. yeres hauyng ſuffycient reaſon to ordre him ſelfe and his goodes / ſelleth a maner / &amp; with the money thereof bieth another maner that is of bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter value &amp; more profytable to him than the fyrſt was / and after he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into the fyrſt maner / bycauſe he was within age at the tyme of the ſale: in that caſe he is bounde to reſtore the money that he recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for the fyrſt maner / excepte the
<pb facs="tcp:282:41"/>
ꝑfites y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the byer receyued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e maner in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane tyme / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he is nat bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to reſtore / for he hath rizt to it by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realm.</p>
            <p>A man maketh a feoffement in fee to another vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> condicyon that the feoffe ſhall nat alyen the lande to none other ꝑſone. And if he do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhalbe lauful for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feoffour &amp; his heyres to reentre / &amp; after the feoffe alyeneth the lande contrary to his condicyon &amp; the feoffoure entreth: in this caſe the feoffour is bounde to reſtore the lande to the alyene. And the reaſon is bycauſe the ſeyd condicyon is voyde in the lawe.</p>
            <p>A tenaunt for terme of lyfe doth waſte: in this caſe he is bounde in conſcience to reſtore him in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercyon of the value of the thynge waſted / immedyately after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waſt done. But of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treble damages n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyeu waſted he is nat bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to
<pb facs="tcp:282:41"/>
make reſtitue. tyll it be recouered agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the law of the realme.</p>
            <p>If a man diſſeaſe another &amp; dye ſeaſed &amp; his heyre e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treth / that heyre and all his heyres after hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the wronge / be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to reſtore the lande to the diſſeyſye &amp; his heyres and no preſcription ne contynua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of long poſſeſſion can helpe in this</p>
            <p>If a man diſſeaſe another (caſe, &amp; dye ſeaſed &amp; his heyre entreth as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe before reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſeaſye dyeth without heyre ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall or ſpecyall: in this caſe the heyres of the diſſeaſour is diſchar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged of any reſtitucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as for the rizt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande to any ꝑſon: for there is none that can clayme that right as heyre to him that the wronge was done vnto: and the lorde of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lande was holden can nat ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it by eſchete / for the grounde of the lawe is / that lande ſhall nat
<pb facs="tcp:282:42"/>
eſchete where the lorde hathe a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt / vpon whom he ſhalbe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to auowe / and therfore the right in this caſe ſhall extyncte to the tenaunte: and alſo in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe a man maye haue right to lande and a tytle of entre alſo: and yet if he dye without heyre the tenaunte ſhall nat be bounde to make reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tucyon to the lorde by way of eſche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te: as if an infant be diſſeaſed / and the diſſeaſour dyeth ſeaſed / ſo that the lande deſcendeth to his heyre / &amp; after the infant dieth without hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re general or ſpecyall: in this caſe the heyre of the diſſeaſoure is nat bounde to reſtore the lande to the lorde by waye of eſchete: &amp; yet the infant might haue entred. And the dyuerſyttes of theſe caſes and of manye other lyke / depende onely vpon the groundes &amp; maxiſmes of the lawes of the realme / &amp; therfore
<pb facs="tcp:282:42"/>
if they be natte knowen / the right can natte be knowen. But than in what maner a man that hath go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or landes wrongefully in any maner / &amp; knoweth nat to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ought to make reſtitucyon / ſhall ordre him ſelfe for diſcharge of his conſcyence haue ben dyuers opiny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons / ſome men haue thoughte in tyme paſt / that if the party ſo bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den to reſtitucyon / opteyned a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro Rome / that ſome por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon therof ſhulde be dyſpoſed in ſuche wyſe / as it ſhulde be therein aſſygned that it ſhulde ſuffyce: &amp; I thynke that no leſſe porcyon than the whole coulde neuer haue ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced: But if a man accordynge to ſuche diſpenſacyon dyſpoſed the whole value in ſuche vſe as the diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>penſacyon lymyted: I thynke it ſuffyced if the partye that ſhulde reſtore / thought the vſe lymited in
<pb facs="tcp:282:43"/>
the dyſpenſacyon ſo charytable / that he thought his conſcye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was thereby dyſcharged. But if he thought a nother vſe more charita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble he might / &amp; yet may dyſpoſe it accordingly if he wyll / and let the dyſpenſacyon alone: And yet the people haue ben brought in belefe that in ſuche caſe reſtitucyon muſt of neceſſytie be made by auctory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of ſuche a dyſpenſacyon / orels at the leſt by counſell of his ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father. And if it be ſo done / I wyll nat ſaye but that it is righte well done / ſo that the counſell ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſfye the conſcyence of him that ſhall do it: But if they gyue coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell that ſuche goodes ſhall be dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in ſuch maner / that after the conſcience of him that muſt reſtore is nat moſt charytable / as for ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge of trentalles / kepynge of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byttes
<pb facs="tcp:282:43"/>
/ fyndyng of ſcolers / or ſuch other. And he therfore that muſte reſtore refuſe that counſell / and diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe it to ſuche vſe as his conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſerueth him beſte to: as percaſe to releue poore men in extreme neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſytie: to make high wayes / or ſuch other lyke. I thynke he taketh the better waye / and that he is therby clerely dyſcharged in conſcyence. Howe be it if he take to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome of the clergye or ſome laye men in whoſe conſcyence he hathe good truſt to gyue him counſell therin: I thynke he dothe the better / but that he ſhulde be enforced of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſytie either to dyſpoſe it only after as ſuche dyſpenſacyon fro Rome haue apoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in tyme paſt / or elles as ſome ſpyrituall counſell ſhulde appoynte and in non other maner
<pb facs="tcp:282:44"/>
there is no cauſe ne aſſured grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d why it ſhulde be ſo. And I haue ſhewed you my conſeyte in theſe maters before reherſed / to none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intent / but that I wold gyue you occaſyon to helpe / if ye coulde to haue ſuch maters ordered / here after in ſuche maner / as ſhall be thought moſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſure of god and to the helth of the ſoules of the people / al couetyce &amp; ſyngularytie layd aparte. For ſurely right gret parcyalytie hath ben ſene in ſuche maters in tyme paſt: but yet there be ſome caſes wherin many men and that ſuch men as haue ben no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably lerned haue douted in / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſtitucyon ſhulde be made to the partye that ought it or nat: as in caſe that a man wyn money by vſury / or at dyſe or cardes / or ſuch other vnlaufull games / whether reſtitucyon oughte to be made in
<pb facs="tcp:282:44"/>
ſuch caſes to the partye ſelfe or nat bycauſe he was partye to the ſame offence / &amp; many haue thought nay but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it muſt be dyſpoſed in ſome other good charytable vſe. And I can right well agree to their opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyon therin: But I thynke verily that if a man wyn money of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by falſe dyſe or other falſhed / that he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in that caſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore it to the partye ſelfe: for the partye ſhall in that caſe haue an ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon at the kinges lawes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that falſhed and recouer his damages.</p>
            <p>And furthermore I wyll ſhewe ſome caſes where the lawes of the realme / &amp; the lawes which the cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gye do oft folowe in reſtitucyons: do varye / whereby euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may lyghtely coniecture / that there be many moo that they varye in: if they were wel &amp; dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſerched.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt if a man bye a thyng in ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:45"/>
market he is nat bounden after the lawes of the realme to reſtore it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine / onleſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he know at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of the bargeyne that he that ſolde it had no right in the goodes. And yet after the ſeyde other lawes he is bounden to reſtore it if he come to the knowlege after who is the very owner. And that he may nat without dedly ſynne holde that is bought. And that is nat ſo in this realme. Alſo if a man bye landes with the churches moneye in his owne name / and to his owne vſe / the landes after the lawes of the realme be his. And he is nat bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to reſtore the landes to the churche but the money only. And yet after the lawe Canon / the lande in that caſe is the churches landes bycau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe it is boughte with the churches money. and therfore the lawes con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernynge reſtytucyons wolde be
<pb facs="tcp:282:45"/>
ſene and be dryuen for clereneſſe of conſcyence to a more nerer certayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie than they be yet. And thus I haue ſhewed you ſomewhat of my conceyte concernynge reſtitucyon to gyue other that ſhall ſe this let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to treate further of that mater herafter. And now wyll I ſomwhat ſpeke of the declarynge of Scrypture.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ Who hathe power to declare &amp; expounde ſcrypture / and whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>claracyon we be bounde to folowe and whoſe nat. The .vii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>THis queſtyon is of ſo gret difficulty that I ſhal deſyre you to holde me excuſed though I fully ſatiſfy nat your mynd therin for ſurely I wyl proteſt that it paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth my power to ſpeke in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as were neceſſarye to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken / for there be fewe maters as I
<pb facs="tcp:282:46"/>
take it that moore requyreth to be playnely touched &amp; declared than that doth: ne that wolde do more good nowe in this daungerouſe tyme / than that wold do / if it were ſet in a clere &amp; in an vpright way: howbeit I conſyder with all / that if I ſayde nothyng to it / ye wolde ſomewhat merueyl why I did nat anſwere to that queſtyon / as well as to the other contayned in your letter. Therefore to gyue you and other that ſhall happen to ſee this letter / occaſyon to treate moore grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly &amp; more throughly of this mater herafter than I do: I ſhall with good wyl ſay ſomwhat to it. Fyrſt it is to be vnderſtande that there be ſome textes of ſcrypture that be ſo ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; playne in them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues that euery man is bounde to gyue full credence vnto them: for the lytterall ſence is the playne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſytion
<pb facs="tcp:282:46"/>
in it ſelfe: As whan it is ſayde / Mat. primo. This is the booke of the generacyon of Ieſu Chriſt / ſonne of Dauid / ſonne of Abraham: Abraham forſoth begat Iſaac. &amp;c. And who maye make any expoſition vpon theſe wordes but that it muſt nedes be graunted that Ieſu Chriſt was the ſonne of Dauyd / ſonne of Abraham. And that Abraham begat Iſaac: But he ſpeke directly agaynſt the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the goſpell: in ſomoche that if all the clerkes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde wold make any expoſytion to the contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye therof: no man were bounden to beleue them. And they for that expoſytion were worthy to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuered fro the company of al faith full people: for the lytterall ſence is ſo playne agaynſt them / wherin the holyghoſt is alwaye the very auctour &amp; ſpeker: that they ſhulde
<pb facs="tcp:282:47"/>
be without all excuſes / for he that reſyſteth Scrypture / reſyſteth the holy ghoſt. And ſo it is vpon this goſpell: Miſſus eſt angelus. &amp;c. An angell was ſent fro god into a cytie of Galylye that had to name Nazareth / to a vyrgin eſpouſed to a man called Ioſeph of the houſe of Dauyd. And the name of the vyrgin was Marye. And who maye ſaye therfore that the angell was nat ſent fro god to the vyrgi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mary / or that ſhe was nat eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Ioſeph / or that Ioſeph was nat of the houſe of Dauyd: but he playnly denyed the texte: for the texte is ſo playne in it ſelfe that it nedeth therein no declaracyon.</p>
            <p>And ſo it is in the mooſt parte of all the Scrypture / both of the old teſtament and new. But yet there be ſome other textes in Scryptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re whiche be nat ſo euydente and
<pb facs="tcp:282:47"/>
playne / as thoſe and manye other be / and yet if they be truly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande / accordynge to the mynde of the maker / that is to ſay / of our maiſter Chriſte / the lytterall ſence of them is as true as the other that be moſte playne / as it is of thys texte. Mat. vi. Ego dico vobis non iurare omnino: I ſay to you ſwere nat for euery cauſe / neyther by heuen / for it is the Throne of god: nor by the erthe / for it is the ſeate for his fete: neyther by Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem / for it is the Cytie of the greate kynge / nor by thy heedde thou ſhalt nat ſwere: for thou canſt nat make one here whyte or blacke Let theſe be youre wordes: It is it is / it is natte / it is nat. Forſoth whatſoeuer is more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this / it is of euyl. Thus farre goth the ſayd text of Mat. vi. before reherſed / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:282:48"/>
Alſo of this texte that is Mar. xvi</p>
            <p>He that beleueth and is baptyſed ſhalbe ſafe. And therfore he that bi reaſon of the ſeyd fyrſt text Mat. v. wolde thinke it were nat lauful to him to ſwere in any caſe / were foule diſceiued: for i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treis wher othes haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſed for tryall of the trouth / euery man is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to ſwere accordynge to the lawes: for the tryall of the trouth / for els iuſtyce ſhulde many tymes periſſh And in lykewiſe if any man by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſeyd other text. Mat. xvi wolde ſay that if a man byleued &amp; were baptyſed / that he ſhulde be ſaued though he dyd no good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes / where he had tyme conuenye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t after his baptyſme to haue done them / he were alſo farre diſceyued wherfore it wer good for him that wer in dout in thoſe caſes or other lyke / as be concernynge ſcrypture
<pb facs="tcp:282:48"/>
to aſke counſell of ſome of the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye that as he thynketh be ſuffycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently lerned in ſcrypture / lyke as it is conuenyent in doutes of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyke to aſke counſell of doctoures of Phiſyke / or in doutes of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall law to aſke counſell of them that be lerned in the temporal law And if he in any dout of ſcrypture aſke counſell of ſuch clerkes as he thynketh be ſuffycyently lerned in ſcrypture / &amp; they inſtruct hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other wyſe than the true vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge of the ſcrypture is / yet that ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth for him / ſo it be nat dyrectly a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſt the lawe of reaſon: for that all men are bounden to knowe.</p>
            <p>But ſyth they of the clergye haue auctorite by the goſpell to preache the goſpell / they ar more bounden to knowe the goſpell tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other But than there be ſome other text<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in the ſcrypture that concerne
<pb facs="tcp:282:49"/>
the auctoritie / power / iuriſdiction and rycheſſe of byſſhops &amp; preſtes as it is vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe textꝭ: Quodcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> liga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eris. &amp;c. Tu es Petrꝰ et ſuꝑ hanc Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>am. &amp;c. Tibi dabo cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. &amp;c. Mat. xvi. Quodcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> liga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueritis. &amp;c. Mat. xviii. Dic ecctie. Mat. xviii. Ecce duo gladii hic. Luc. xxii. &amp;c. Oraui ꝑte Petre vt non deficiat fides tua: et in aliqu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſus. &amp;c. Luc. xxii. Paſce oues meas. Io. xxi. Predicate eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelm oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> creature. Mar, vltio Nolite poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidere au<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> ne<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> arge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Mat x. &amp;c. Qui no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>renu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>crauerit poſſidet oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>aq<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poteſt meꝰ eſſe diſcipulꝰ. luc. 14. ſicut miſit me pr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ego mitto vos Io. xxi. Quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>rum</ex>
               </expan> remiſeritis peta. &amp;c. Io. xx. habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes alime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta &amp; quibꝰ tegamur. &amp;c. i. Timo. vi. Nolite ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gere chriſtos meos. pſ. 44. And many other which I here omit. &amp; if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were in dout vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:282:49"/>
/ what power iuriſdiction poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or lyberte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy ought to haue by the ſeyd textꝭ: or whether ſuch actꝭ &amp; lawꝭ as haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made bi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> princes &amp; their people concernyng ſuche thynges were to be obeyd: or ſuche other lyke, Many men thynke that it were natte the moſt ſureſt way to aſke cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell therin of the lerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the clergi / onles it were of ſome ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guler elect me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that through ſpeciall grace / haue ſeq<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred their myndꝭ fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of all worldly honour &amp; riches: for the af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuch worldli pleaſures ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue blynded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſoreꝭ y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue thought / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the mayntenaunce of the honour of the clergye hath ben a maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the honour of god. And ſo as it were vnder a pretence to maynteyne the honour of god ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue dyſpleaſed god &amp; maynteyned
<pb facs="tcp:282:50"/>
their owne honour &amp; rycheſſe / far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the ſeyde textes / or anye other parte of ſcrypture wyll war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant them to do. This hathe ben ſene in ſome of the clergye / but I truſte it be nat ſo in all / neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to ſpeke ſomewhat further of this mater. I thynke that if anye doute ryſe vpon any text of ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture / be it playne or nat playne con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernyng the fayth or morall lyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the people or nat: orels the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour / lyberty / &amp; ryches of the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye / or any other thyng whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be. if there fall any varya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or vnquyetneſſe thervpon amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the people: as if one doctoure or many / &amp; ſome of the lay people be of one opinyon therin: &amp; other of a nother opinyon / &amp; thervpon dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſyties of opinyons &amp; vnquyet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe amonge the people doo ryſe / that in all theſe caſes / kynges and
<pb facs="tcp:282:50"/>
princes ſhalbe iudges / &amp; haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to pacyfye all ſuche vnquyet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For it appereth Pſal. ii. that it is ſaid thus to kynges &amp; princes O ye kynges / vnderſtande ye: be ye lerned that iudge the worlde. And if it be ſayd that by thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des / Iuge the worlde / that kinges and princes muſt iuge onely vpon temporall thynges: as vpon the bodyes / landes &amp; goodes. And nat vpon any thyng that apperteineth to the ſoule: trewly that is a right great erroure / for it wolde bringe the people in belefe / that the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſours of the apoſtles &amp; diſcyples of Chriſt haue only cure of ſoules &amp; nat kynges &amp; princes. And that is nat ſo: for it is no dout / but if a prince ſuffre his people wylfully breke the lawes of god / or the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of his realme and ſe them nat corrected accordyng to his lawes
<pb facs="tcp:282:51"/>
but that he offendeth god rizt high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thereby as euery man ſhall do / that willyngly &amp; wylfully ſuffreth his ſeruants breke the law of god without correctyon / whan he may well correcte them: and ouer that no man can denye but that euery man is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to procure the ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly helth of his neyghbour by cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeylyng &amp; good example gyuynge to his power as it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Eccl. xvii. God hath gyuen a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to euery man vpon his ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: and ſyth euery man hathe a charge of his neyghbour / it muſt nedes folowe that a kynge hath a more ſpeciall charge ouer his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes: &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is ſpecyally bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to prohibyt all thinges as nigh as he can wherby his ſubiectes ſpiry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall or temporall might haue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to breke the lawes of god: &amp; the charge of the clergy is to my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb facs="tcp:282:51"/>
the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to the people and to preche &amp; teche them howe to pleaſe god &amp; kepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes: &amp; if they be neglygent &amp; do nat ſo / kynges &amp; princes ar bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de them to do it. And if they gyue the people euyll exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple / prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ar bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leue it: let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore iuge whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny curate may truly ſay: the kyng hath only cure of the bodyes of my paryſſhens / but I of their ſoules: for it is no dout but that kynges &amp; princes haue cure and charge ouer both / &amp; that nat only ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules of laye me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but alſo of the ſoules of byſſhops &amp; preſtes: &amp; therfore ſuch vayne ſayengꝭ wolde be prohibyt / for they nouriſſhe &amp; engendre gret pride / and for a further prouf that pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces may pacify all maner of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>q<hi rend="sup">i</hi>etnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may riſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by any maner of occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all
<pb facs="tcp:282:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or temporall. It is ſayde Exo. vi. a wyſe kynge is the ſtableneſſe of his people: wherof it foloweth / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if the vnſtableneſſe come by occaſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any expoſycion of ſcrypture / be it by doctours / prechers / or any other / that kynges haue power to ſtable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And of that it foloweth alſo that if any man wyll preache in ſuch maner that it is lyke to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke vnquietneſſe among the people that the prince maye prohybit him of that prechyng: for he that hath auctoritie to remoue an vnquyet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe preſent: hath auctorite to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uent occaſions wherby ſuch vnqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etneſſe might happen to folow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter amonge his ſubiectes. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore / all men agree that the ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholyque churche maye expounde ſcrypture: &amp; if the clergy can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue that they be the catholyke chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / than it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde
<pb facs="tcp:282:52"/>
it. But if the emperours / kynges &amp; princes / with their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / aſwell of the clergye as of the lay fee make the catholique church and the clergye but a parte of that church: than may the emperoure / kynges &amp; pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces with their people expounde it. But for as moche as the vnyuerſall catholique / people can nat be gathered togyther to make ſuche expoſycion / therfore it ſemeth that kynges &amp; princes who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people haue choſen &amp; agreed to be their rulers &amp; gouernours / and which haue the whole voyces of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people / maye with theire counſell ſpirytuall &amp; temporall make expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycyon of ſuch ſcripture as is dout<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full / ſo as they ſhall thynke to be the true vnderſtandyng of it / and none but they / &amp; that theire ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes be bounden euen by the lawe of god to folowe their expoſycion
<pb facs="tcp:282:53"/>
for the goodneſſe of oure lorde is ſuche that he wyll nat leue his peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple in ſuche doutes but that they maye haue ſome meanes whereby they maye come to the knowlege of the trouth ſo as ſhalbe neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye to their ſaluatyon if they wyll dyſpoſe them to it / and that is by obedyence to their princes whom god hathe appoynted to haue rule ouer them / as is afore ſayde. And here it is to be noted / that there be two maner of powers that kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and princes haue ouer theire ſubiectes: The one is called / Ius regale / that is to ſaye a kyngely gouernaunce: And he that hathe that power maye with his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell make lawes to bynde his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes / and alſo make declaration of Scypture for the good order of his ſubiectes / as nede ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre / for appeaſyng of varyance.
<pb facs="tcp:282:53"/>
The other is called / Ius regale politicum / that is to ſaye a kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and a polytyke gouernaunce. And that is the moſt noble power that any prince hath ouer his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes / and he that ruleth by that power / maye make no Lawe to bynde his ſubiectes without their aſſent / but by their aſſent he maye ſo that the lawes that he maketh be nat agaynſte the lawe of God / nor the lawe of reaſon: And this power hathe the kynges grace in this Realme: where he by aſſente of his lordes ſpirytuall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perall: and of his commons ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered togyther by his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement in his parlyamente maye make lawes to bynde the people And of thoſe lawꝭ there nedeth no ꝓclamation / bicauſe they be made by all the people / for the ꝑliament
<pb facs="tcp:282:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſo gathered togyther / the people repreſenteth the eſtate of al the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple within this realme / that is to ſay of the whole catholyque chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che therof. And why ſhuld nat the parlyament than whiche repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the whole catholyke churche of Englande expounde ſcrypture rather than the conuocacyon whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che repreſenteth onely the ſtate of the clergy: &amp; ouer that me thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to pretende that at a generall counſell anye other ſhulde be iuges but kynges &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces &amp; ſuche as they wyll appoynte vnder them to bere voyces therin: ſeynge that they haue the power &amp; voyce of the whole people of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom / which is the catholyque churche as is ſayde before: and I thynke verily that generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels ſhall do lytell good tyll chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> princes wyl knowe their owne po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer
<pb facs="tcp:282:54"/>
&amp; the auctorite that they haue receyued of god ouer his people / and that they ſet the clergy in ſuch power as they ought to haue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of god without diminiſſhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of it in any maner: &amp; to ſe alſo that they haue no more but as ſhall be thoughte expedyent for the comen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>welth / &amp; alſo for the helth of their owne ſoules &amp; of the people. And ſurely it is greatly to be douted / that the power that byſſhoppes of Rome haue claymed in tyme paſt ouer princes &amp; other byſſhoppes / haue ben a great occaſyon of the deſolacyon of manye countreys that nowe be eſtemed amonge vs latyns as ſciſmatykes &amp; deſperate perſones. And therfore it is good that the Emperour and all chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kynges &amp; princes &amp; the clergy alſo loke wel vpon the matter and to ſe whether the ſeyd countreyes were
<pb facs="tcp:282:55"/>
nat moſt pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cypally eſtemed as he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retykes &amp; ſcyſmatykꝭ bycauſe they we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fro the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Rome / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any other cauſe: &amp; whether ther was ſuch dilygence charitie &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe ſhewed to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as ought to haue ben ſhewed: or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were extremely or happe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / maliciouſly ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled by excomu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nycatyons &amp; interdictions as men vnworthy the confort of chriſtꝭ paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo wold fall fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the heed of Chriſtes church: And yet vndoutedly the ſaluatyon or dampnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth nat in that poynte / whether Rome be the hed of chriſtes church or nat. And I meane all this that I haue ſaid of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Grecyans / of the Suria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Iacobytꝭ / of the Neſtorians wherof gret ꝑte be now in Percye which is heed enemy to the curſed turkꝭ Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armins: The georgia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:282:55"/>
that be gret archers and very apte me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the warre: Of the Abaſynes otherwyſe called Indyans: &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maronytꝭ &amp; of theſe Maronytes: Bernard deane of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunce in his boke of his iorney to Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / writeth that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeyd Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ronytꝭ about. v. C. yeres were he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retykꝭ ſeperated fro the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of faythfull people: but at the laſt he ſayth / that through the inſpiracyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god / they turned to their owne hertes: &amp; confeſſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that they had er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red were no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred agayne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Rome: &amp; retur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholyke fayth &amp; that thervpon though all the byſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhops of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eſt ꝑtes &amp; the chefe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of other nacions vſe no ringꝭ miters ne biſhops ſtaues: yet ſaith he that theſe Maronites vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al as we do i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their diuyne ſeruyces &amp; miniſtration of the ſacramentes.
<pb facs="tcp:282:56"/>
And thus were they ſeyth he refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: but yet it may be douted whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther they were natte reformed to more pride than they had before: and I beſeche oure lorde that all chriſten princes through the inſpy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration of god may encourage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe to bringe all the ſeyde people and vs alſo to the verye true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence of Chriſt &amp; of his lawes / &amp; to a true vnderſtandyng / and a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoute folowynge of his ſcrypture all worldly pompe: pride / &amp; deſyre of worldly honoure / ſpecyally in the clergy / whiche ought to be the lyghte &amp; leders of the laye people / vtterly diſpyſed and ſet a parte aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moch as in them is: &amp; than I dout nat but that gret charytie &amp; grace ſhal ſhortly after appere amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the people. And than forthermore if a man be in doute vpon any thynge concernynge ſcrypture as is ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:282:56"/>
before / and he hathe no counſell to inſtructe hym therin / or els if there be counſell / the counſell va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryeth amonge them ſelfe as is ſaid before. And princes haue no tyme yet to determyne the mater. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is good that he ſo beyng in dout lyfte vp his herte to god / and aſke counſell of him: and if he do ſo / vndoutedly our lorde wyll ſo hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe him and aſſyſt him therin / that he ſhall nat erre / ne be diſceyued: For it is written. ii. Paralip. xx. Cum ignoremus quid facere / de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beamꝰ hoc ſolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſidui habemus vt oculi noſtri ad te dirigantur.</p>
            <p>That is to ſaye / Lorde / whan we be ignorant &amp; wot nat what to do / this only remayneth to vs for our confort / that we lyft our eyen vp to the. And if we do ſo we may truſt verily that his helpe and counſell wil neuer fayle vs / but wyll bring
<pb facs="tcp:282:57"/>
vs to the knowlege of that that is neceſſarye for vs.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An anſwere to dyuerſe ſhorte particuler queſtions conteyned in the letter. The .viii. chapiter.</head>
            <p>TO all the ſhorte partyculer queſtions co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in your letter. I wyll brefely as I can ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke anſwer in this .viii. cha. And as to the fyrſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd particuler queſtyons / I thinke that kynges and princes might haue prohybyt the clergy to haue ordeyned amon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patryarkes / cardnials / or any other degree i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the clergye but onely byſſhops / preſtes &amp; deako<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</p>
            <p>Alſo if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyces with cure i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this realme / they both after the old groundes of the law of the realme had ben voide / &amp; this voydance was called ceſſyon
<pb facs="tcp:282:57"/>
but in ꝓceſſe of tyme lycenſes wer opteyned from Rome to haue two benefices. And thoſe lyce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes by po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer of the clergy were iuged to be good / and ſo the lawe and cuſtom of the Realme in that poynte was broken. And yet it wyll be verye harde to proue it by the lawe / that it ſhulde haue ben ſo. And neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe by reaſon therof / the ſeyde grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de was altered to this effect / that if a man toke two benefyces without dyſpenſacyon fro Rome / that both benefyces ſhuld be voyd but if the firſt grounde were clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reuyued &amp; none to haue but one benefyce / it were well done: for the breking of that grounde hath done gret hurte / &amp; than it might ther v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon be ꝓuided that he that is more worthy ſhuld haue the better bene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce &amp; no vnyon of benefyces to be made in tyme to come.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:282:58"/>Alſo though the apoſtles &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyples of Chriſt and theyr ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours had auctorite by the goſpell to preche the goſpell: yet that any one of them ſhulde haue auctorite to prohybyt another of them of pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chyng / appereth nat by the goſpel but in caſe that any take vpon him to preche &amp; teche any thyng agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the catholycall faythe / to the parell and daunger of the kynges ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes / and whereby ſcyſmes and va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryaunces be lyke to folowe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge his people: ſuche of the clergye as knoweth it / ar bounde to enforme the kyng of it / &amp; than he thervpon may prohibyt them of prechyng / &amp; ſee them corrected as the caſe requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth. But if the rulers in the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye / ſhulde haue full auctoritie to make ſuch prohibicyons / it might be that abuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the clergy ſhuld nat be ſo well touched as charytie
<pb facs="tcp:282:58"/>
wolde they ſhulde be / &amp; that might be greate hurte &amp; trouble to all the realme / and that the kyng and his parlyament hath auctorite to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke that prohibycyon. The clergye of engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de knewe right well wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they laboured in the parlyament / that commyſſyons ſhuld be grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſheryffes to areſt prechers of hereſy. Anno .ii. Rich. ii. ſtat. ii. Cap. vltimo.</p>
            <p>And as to that opinyon that ye write to me of / whether the ſoules that be dyſceſſed in grace be nowe in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / or that they reſt for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne tyme in a place to them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted by god: tyll that the tyme of the generail reſurrectyon ſhall come / ſo that the bodye &amp; the ſoule may be ioyned togyther / and than they both togyther to go to heuen and haue the fruycyon of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heed &amp; nat before. Verily I haue
<pb facs="tcp:282:59"/>
herde but lytell ſpekynge thereof many a daye. For ſcrypture is ſo playne therin / And is nowe ſo well knowen to many by the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that it is come in to the Englyſſhe tonge / that dyuers that haue dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therin in tymes paſt / be nowe contented and holde theire peaſe. And parte of the textes that haue ſomewhat ſtablyſſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therin / I ſhall brefely recyte. One texte is Pſal. C.xxvi. where it is ſayde:</p>
            <p>Cum dederit dilectis ſuis ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ecce hereditas domini: filii merces: fructus ventris. That is whan our lorde hath gyuen to his beloued / ſlepe: lo the inherytance of oure lorde / the rewarde of the ſonne / and the frute of the wom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be: whiche is thus moche to ſaye: That whan oure lorde hath taken a ryghtwyſe man / nat bounde to anye ſynne / ne to anye payne for
<pb facs="tcp:282:59"/>
ſynne / by the ſlepe of naturall deth that forthwith cometh the enhery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce of god / the rewarde of the ſonne of god: That is to ſaye / the eternall glorie of heuen. And the frute of the wombe / which is chriſt Another texte is this: oure lorde ſayde to his diſcyples. Ioh. xiii. If I go fro you / and prepayre to you a place / I wyll come agayne and take you to my ſelfe / That where I am / you ſhalbe. And ſo ſyth he is in heuen / it muſte nedes folow that they be there with him.</p>
            <p>And alſo he ſayde. Iohannis xvii. Father / thoſe that thou haſt gyuen to me / I wyll / that where I am / that they ſhall be with me that they ſhall ſee my clereneſſe whiche thou haſte gyuen me.</p>
            <p>And alſo it appereth Apocalip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis .xiiii. That Saynte Iohan
<pb facs="tcp:282:60"/>
ſawe a Lambe ſtandynge on the mounte of Syon / and with him a hundreth and .xliiii. M. hauyng his name &amp; the name of his father / written in their foreheeddes: and they ſang as it had be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a newe ſong before the ſete / and before the .iiii. beſtes &amp; ſeygnyours / that no man coulde ſaye but thoſe .C.xliiii. M that were bought fro the erth. And in that he ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wer bought fro the erthe / it appereth that they were the ſoules of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche had lyued before in erth / whiche ſaynt Iohan ſawe en vyſyon ſtandynge before god. And it can nat be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they were there in bodye and ſoule / but in ſoule only. It appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth alſo in the goſpell that Lazar was in the boſome of Abraham.</p>
            <p>And it is no doute but that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of Abraham that tyme ſlepte. By theſe textes and dyuers other
<pb facs="tcp:282:60"/>
nat here reherſed / that matter is well appeſed / ſo that I wolde nat haue written to you anye thynge therin / but that ye deſyred me in your letter ſo to do.</p>
            <p>Alſo there be ſome here aboute the cytie that thynke that they that endeuour them ſelfe to withdraw the mindes of the people ſomwhat fro the inordynate goynge on pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grymages / prayeng to ſayntes / &amp; worſhippynge of them: And fro worſhippynge of ymages and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyques: &amp; ſtyrre theym to ſet theyr myndes and their deuocion / holly and fully in Chriſt our ſauyour / of whom all goodneſſe cometh in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and in erth / do more to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne the true honour to our lady and to other ſayntes / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they that endeuour them ſelfe to maynteyne ſuch thynges after the old faſhion
<pb facs="tcp:282:61"/>
all that they can: for ſayntes wold haue no honour gyuen to them / ne any truſt put in them: but it were princypally for Chriſte and to his honoure. And they ſaye alſo that no man may with clere conſcyence moue the people to contynue ſuche thinges after the olde maner. But they moue theym lykewyſe to be well ware of ſuche parelles and daungers / as they maye lyghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye fall in to by occaſyon thereof: but they take good hede. And I thynke verily that it is euen true as they ſaye in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>Alſo it is true that ther be right manye here aboute the Cytie as well of the clergye / as of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men people / that thynke that ſome doctours that haue written vpon Scrypture in tyme paſt / haue in thynges concernynge the honoure power / lybertye / and rycheſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:282:61"/>
the Clergye exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Scrypture / verye farre i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fauour of the clergy: But vpon all places of Scryptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re that concerne the faythe and the morall lyuynge of the people: they thynke the doctoures haue taken the true ſence of it / and veryly I ſuppoſe it is euen as they ſaye.</p>
            <p>And I thynke further that it were right expedyent that it ſhulde be ofte declared and made manyfeſt to the people / that Scrypture is the thinge that is of hygheſt aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytie in the churche of god / and that it is alwaye trewe and maye neuer be denyed / &amp; that the more it is knowen and loued / the more goodneſſe ſhall folowe of it: for it is the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacion of the church: the ſhelde of the world: the ſubuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fende / the ladder to paradice and the very true fode of the ſoule and is alſo of more vertue &amp; ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:282:62"/>
ſtrength / than ar the ſayengꝭ of all doctours and ſayntes / where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bleſſed be they that can wel fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe it: And now haue I accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to your deſyre ſhewed you my conceyte to all the arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayned in your letter. And thus I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit you to oure lorde Ieſu. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <argument>
               <p>¶ Here endeth the anſwere to the letter. And here foloweth the table of the Chapiters.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:282:62"/>
            <head>The table of the chapiters</head>
            <list>
               <item>wHether the kynge by that he is recognyſed to be ſupreme heed vnder god vpon erth of the church of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / haue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any new power gyuen hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer his ſubiectes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had nat before. The fyrſt cha.</item>
               <item>¶ Of dyuers thynges concerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the power of the byſſhop of Rome and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtatutes made in the .xxv. yere &amp; .xxvi. yere of kynge Henry the eyght / which treate of the ſayd power. The .ii. chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Of prayenge to ſayntes and worſhyppynge of theym. The thyrde cha.</item>
               <item>¶ Whether there be any opinyon among the people / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there be ſome abuſyons concernynge the maſſe. The fourth Cha.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:282:63"/>¶ Of pardons and abſolutions. The .v. Chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ Of reſtitucyon. The .vi. chap.</item>
               <item>¶ Who hathe power to declare &amp; expounde ſcrypture / and whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>claracyon we be bounde to folowe and whoſe nat. The .vii. chapiter.</item>
               <item>¶ An anſwere to dyuerſe ſhorte particuler queſtions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in the letter. The .viii. chap.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶ The ende of the table.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Printed at London by Tho. Godfray.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio Regali.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:282:63"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
